Weiwei Zhan, Ph.D.

Incoming Assistant Professor at University of Central Florida Postdoctoral Fellow, The University of Texas at Austin NHERI DesignSafe, Texas Advanced Computing Center Room 1.463, 10100 Burnet Rd, Austin, TX 78758

Tel: 864-556-1193 | Email: weiwei.zhan@austin.utexas.edu

Website: https://weiwei-zhan.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie primarily in understanding the complex hazard-infrastructure-human interactions and advancing urban intelligence and resilience. I study multiple geological hazards, such as earthquakes, landslides, and liquefaction, and their effects on infrastructure systems. I use a wide range of approaches, including remote sensing, signal processing, geomaterial testing, computational simulation, statistical learning, machine learning, and deep learning. Main research thrusts include site-specific and regional assessment of earthquake site responses, ground-motion modeling, near-real-time liquefaction hazard assessment, landslide mechanism and mitigation, geospatial surrogate modeling, and uncertainty quantification.

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

Jan. 2023 – Dec. 2023	Postdoctoral Fellow	University of Texas at Austin, USA
	Topic: HPC applications in natura	l hazard engineering
	Advisor: Prof. Ellen Rathje	
Mar. 2021- Dec. 2022	Postdoctoral Scholar	Tufts University, USA
	Topic: Geospatial natural hazard n	nodeling and uncertainty quantification
	Advisor: Prof. Laurie Baise	
Jan. 2017 – Dec 2020	Graduate Research Assistant	Clemson University, USA
	Topic: Probabilistic liquefaction ri	isk assessment
	Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Qiushi Chen	
Sep. 2014 – Dec 2016	Graduate Research Assistant	Chengdu University of Technology, China
	Topic: Landslide mechanism and r	isk mitigation design
	Advisors: Prof. Xuanmei Fan, Prof.	f. Runqiu Huang

EDUCATION

2020	Ph.D. in Civil Engineering	Clemson University, USA
	Thesis: Data-driven assessment of site respon	nses at liquefiable sites
	Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Qiushi Chen	
2019	M.Sc. in Civil Engineering (non-thesis)	Clemson University, USA
	Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Qiushi Chen	
2014	B.S. in Geological Engineering	Chengdu University of Technology, China
	Thesis: Statistical modeling of coseismic land	dslide mobility
	Advisors: Prof. Xiangjun Pei, Prof. Weile Li	

AWARDS & HONORS

2022	Travel Grant for 2022 SimCenter Symposium, NHERI SimCenter (UC Berkeley)
2022	Travel Grant for 12NCEE, Earthquake Engineering Research Institute (EERI)
2016	National Scholarship, Ministry of Education of China

2016	Travel Grant for International Rockslides School, Chengdu University of Technology
2014	Top 10 Bachelor's Thesis (10/8000), Chengdu University of Technology
2014	Meritorious Mention in National Mathematical Modeling Contest, Madio.net
2013	Honorable Mention in the International Mathematics Modeling Competition (MCM/ICM)
	Consortium for Mathematics and Its Application (COMAP)
2012	Excellent Volunteer, Environmental Protection Agency of Sichuan Province

TEACHING & MENTORING

Teaching	
2018 - 2020	Instructor, Soil Mechanics Lab
2020	Teaching Assistant, Geotechnical Engineering
2018 - 2019	Teaching Assistant, Earth Slopes and Retaining Structures
2019	Teaching Assistant, Geotechnical Design
2018	Teaching Assistant, Data Mining for System Analytics
2018	Teaching Assistant, Uncertainty Modeling in Risk Engineering
2017	Teaching Assistant, Fundamentals of Risk Engineering
Mentoring	
2021 - 2022	Mentor for two Ph.D. students at Tufts Univ. (Marshall Pontrelli & Christina Sanon),
	"Geospatial Database and Modeling"
2020	Mentor for two undergraduate student interns at Clemson Univ. (William Luce &
	Christopher Michael Overton), "Mechanical Properties of Lunar Regolith Simulants"
2019	Mentor for three undergraduate student interns at Clemson Univ. (Andrew Bradley, Jason
	Timberlake, & William Luce), "CT morphology for Martian Regolith Simulants"
2018	Mentor for three high school student interns at South Carolina Governor's School for
	Science and Mathematics (Frankie Hawkesworth, Olivia Hilferty, & Jason Gleaton),
	"Strength Tests of Bio-Cemented Martian Regolith Simulants"

SUCCESSFUL PROPOSALS & GRANTS

2022	U.S. Geological Survey Earthquake Hazards Program External Grant, G23AP00093
	HVSR Site Terms for Nonergodic Ground Motion Models, \$96,583
	(PI: Laurie Baise & James Kaklamanos)
2022	U.S. Geological Survey Earthquake Hazards Program External Grant, G23AP00094
	Basin Effects Model Using Multi-Scale Geospatial Data, \$95,123
	(PI: Laurie Baise & James Kaklamanos)
2021	U.S. Geological Survey Earthquake Hazards Program External Grant, G22AP00048
	Innovative Data-Driven Frameworks for Geospatial Ground Failure Models, \$97,123
	(PI: Laurie Baise & Babak Moaveni)
2021	U.S. Geological Survey Earthquake Hazards Program External Grant
	Machine Learning Framework for Site Amplification Modeling (Recommended but not
	funded due to insufficient funds), PI: Laurie Baise & James Kaklamanos

SUBMITTED PAPERS

- 3. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Kaklamanos J. A geospatial model for site response complexity. *Bulletin of the Seismological Society of America*. (under revision)
- 2. Zhan W, Cochran E. Reducing aleatory uncertainty of ground-motion modeling using gradient boosting

- model and feature selection techniques. Bulletin of the Seismological Society of America. (under revision)
- 1. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Moaveni B. A Quantifying Uncertainty Framework for Geospatial Natural Hazard Modeling. *Engineering Geology*. (submitted)

PAPERS IN PREPARATION

- 2. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Moaveni B, Chansky A, et al. Updating Global Geospatial Liquefaction Models with a Focus on Feature Engineering. Targeting *Engineering Geology*.
- 1. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Moaveni B, Chansky A, et al. OpenLIQ: An Open-Source Geospatial Dataset for Global Liquefaction Hazard Assessment. Targeting *Earthquake Spectra*.

PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL PAPERS

(*corresponding author)

- 14. Zhang L, **Zhan W**, Wang L* (2023). Probabilistic Seismic Analyses of Earthen Levees with Finite Element Modeling. *Marine Georesources & Geotechnology*, 1-8.
- 13. Wu R, Guo C*, Ni J, Song D, **Zhan W**, Zhong N, Yang Z, Li X, Yan Y (2023). Ancient landslide river damming event in the Batang fault zone, Tibetan Plateau. *Bulletin of Engineering Geology and the Environment*, 82(1): 25.
- 12. Li W, **Zhan W***, Lu H, Xu Q, Pei X, Wang D, Huang R, Ge D (2022). Precursors to large rockslides visible on optical remote-sensing images and their implications for landslide early detection. *Landslides*, DOI 10.1007/s10346-022-01960-1.
- 11. Lu J, Li W*, **Zhan W**, Tie Y (2022). Distribution and mobility of co-seismic landslides triggered by the 2018 Hokkaido earthquake in Japan. *Remote Sensing*, 14, 3957.
- 10. **Zhan W**, Chen Q* (2022). Nonlinear site response on liquefiable sites: insights from downhole seismic observations. *Engineering Geology*, Article 106610.
- 9. Luo Y, Xu Q, **Zhan W**, Grelle G (2022). Seismic hazard prediction using multispectral amplification maps in a complex topographic area: A case study of Qiaozhuang town, Sichuan Province, Southwest China. *Journal of Mountain Science*, 19: 726–739.
- 8. Shan S, Pei X, **Zhan W*** (2021). Estimating deformation modulus and bearing capacity of deep soils from dynamic penetration test. *Advances in Civil Engineering*, Article 1082050.
- Zhan W, Chen Q* (2021). Accelerogram-based method for quick assessment of liquefaction occurrence.
 Journal of Geotechnical and Geoenvironmental Engineering, 147 (8): 04021060.
- 6. Gao G, Meguid MA, Chouinard LE, **Zhan W** (2021). Dynamic disintegration processes accompanying transport of an earthquake-induced landslide. *Landslides*, 18 (3): 909-933.
- Fan X, Zhan W*, Dong X, van Westen C, Xu Q, Dai L, Yang Q, Huang R, Havenith HB (2018).
 Analyzing successive landslide dam formation by different triggering mechanisms: The case of the Tangjiawan landslide, Sichuan, China. *Engineering Geology*, 243: 128-144.
- 4. Fan X*, Scaringi G, Xu Q, **Zhan W**, Dai L, Li Y, Pei X, Yang Q, Huang R (2018). Coseismic landslides triggered by the 8th August 2017 M s 7.0 Jiuzhaigou earthquake (Sichuan, China): factors controlling their spatial distribution and implications for the seismogenic blind fault identification. *Landslides*, 15(5): 967-983.
- 3. Meng X, Pei X*, Huang R, Cui S, Zhu L, **Zhan W** (2018). Shear behaviors of rock mass in the interlayer fault zone of Daguangbao landslide. *Journal of Engineering Geology*, 26 (2): 309-318. (in Chinese)
- 2. **Zhan W**, Fan X*, Huang R, Pei X, Xu Q, Li W (2017). Empirical prediction for travel distance of channelized rock avalanches in the Wenchuan earthquake area. *Natural Hazards & Earth System Sciences*, 17(6): 833-844.

1. **Zhan W**, Huang R, Pei X, Li W (2017). Empirical prediction model for movement distance of gully-type rock avalanches. *Journal of Engineering Geology*, 25 (1): 154-163. (*in Chinese*)

PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PAPERS

- 5. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Kaklamanos J (2023). Predicting Within-Site Variability of Seismic Site Response Using a Geospatial Modeling Approach, *Geo-Risk 2023*, Arlington, Virginia, July 23-26, 2023. (*feature paper & plenary presentation*, 9 of 163 papers)
- 4. **Zhan W**, Zhang L, Wang L (2023). Probabilistic Assessment of Earthen Levees Considering Soil Spatial Variability, *Geo-Risk 2023*, Arlington, Virginia, July 23-26, 2023. (*accepted*)
- 3. **Zhan W**, Chen Q (2022). Evaluation of an accelerogram-based liquefaction detection method using continuous earthquake recordings. *GeoCalgary 2022*, Calgary, Canada, October 2-5, 2022.
- Zhan W, Chen Q (2021). Assessment of liquefaction effects on ground motion frequency parameters for accelerogram-based liquefaction detection, *American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE) Geotechnical* Engineering for Extreme Events (GeoExtreme) 2021, Savannah, GA, USA, November 7-10, 2021.
- 1. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Chen Q, Juang CH, Miao F (2021). Effects of liquefaction-affected ground motions on building fragility curves, *17th World Conference on Earthquake Engineering*, Sendai, Japan, September 27-October 2, 2021.

PRESENTATIONS

(*presenter)

- 15. **Zhan W***, Baise LG, Moaveni B (2023). Updating Global Geospatial Liquefaction Models: with Focus on Uncertainty Quantification and Feature Engineering, *USGS Geologic Hazards Science Center Research Seminar*, Golden, Colorado, USA, January 31, 2023 (*Invited seminar talk*).
- 14. **Zhan W***, Baise LG, Moaveni B, Chansky A, et al (2023). Updating Global Geospatial Liquefaction Models with a Focus on Feature Engineering. *Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2023 Annual Meeting*, San Juan, Puerto Rico, April 17-20, 2023. (*Oral presentation*)
- 13. **Zhan W***, Baise LG, Moaveni B (2023). How to Quantify Uncertainties for Logistic-Regression-Based Geospatial Natural Hazard Models? *Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2023 Annual Meeting*, San Juan, Puerto Rico, April 17-20, 2023. (*Poster presentation*)
- 12. Asadi A*, Baise LG, Chatterjee S, **Zhan W**, Chansky A, Moaveni B (2023). Global Geospatial Modeling of Earthquake-Induced Soil Liquefaction Using a System of Voting Machine Learning Classifiers. *Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2023 Annual Meeting*, San Juan, Puerto Rico, April 17-20, 2023. (*Oral presentation*)
- 11. **Zhan W***, Baise LG, Moaveni B (2022). Quantifying epistemic uncertainty for global geospatial liquefaction models, *2022 SimCenter Symposium*, Austin, Texas, USA, November 3-4, 2022. (*Oral presentation*)
- 10. **Zhan W***, Baise LG, Moaveni B (2022). Uncertainty quantification for global geospatial liquefaction models, *Natural Hazards Research Summit 2022*, Washington, DC, USA, October 6-7, 2022. (*Poster presentation*)
- 9. **Zhan W***, Baise LG, Kaklamanos J (2022). A geospatial model for predicting site response complexity. *Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2022 Annual Meeting*, Bellevue, Washington, USA, April 19-23, 2022. (*Oral presentation*)
- 8. **Zhan W***, Baise LG, Kaklamanos J (2022). Ground-motion modeling using machine learning techniques and geospatial proxies. *Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2022 Annual Meeting*, Bellevue, Washington, USA, April 19-23, 2022. (*Poster presentation*)
- 7. Pontrelli MA*, Baise LG, Ebel JE, Mabee SB, Zhan W (2022). Geology and Geomorphology Based f0

- Model of New England. Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2022 Annual Meeting, Bellevue, Washington, USA, April 19-23, 2022. (Poster presentation)
- 6. Zhan W*, Chen Q (2021). Assessment of liquefaction effects on ground motion frequency parameters for accelerogram-based liquefaction detection, American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE) Geotechnical Engineering for Extreme Events (GeoExtreme) 2021, Savannah, GA, USA, November 7-10, 2021. (Oral presentation)
- 5. **Zhan W***, Baise LG, Chen Q, Juang CH, Miao F (2021). Effects of liquefaction-affected ground motions on building fragility curves, *17th World Conference on Earthquake Engineering*, Sendai, Japan, September 27-October 2, 2021. (*Virtual poster presentation*)
- 4. Gong, W, **Zhan W***, Wang L, Juang CH (2021). Design of Stabilizing Piles in Earth Slopes Considering Design Robustness, *Engineering Mechanics Institute Conference/Probabilistic Mechanics and Reliability (EMI/PMC) 2021 Conference*, Columbia University, New York City, USA, May 25-28, 2021. (*Virtual oral presentation*)
- 3. **Zhan W***, Chen Q (2020). Quick detection of subsoil liquefaction using accelerograms. *2020 AGU Fall Meeting*, San Francisco, CA, USA, December 7-11, 2020. (*Virtual oral presentation*)
- 2. **Zhan W***, Chen Q (2020). Coseismic and long-term changes of site response on liquefiable sites: a case study of Onahama Port Array in Japan. *2020 Eastern Section of the Seismological Society of America (ES-SSA) Annual Meeting*, Atlanta, GA, USA, October 12-16, 2020. (*Virtual oral presentation*)
- 1. **Zhan W***, Huang R, Pei X (2015). Study on the Site Effects of Large-scale Landslide movement triggered by Wenchuan Earthquake, *Engineering Geological Disaster Prevention Academic Conference*, Shanghai, China, October 12-14, 2015. (*Oral presentation in Chinese*)

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

Convener	2022 SSA Session "Advances in Geospatial Modeling of Seismic Hazards"
Convener	2022 SSA Special Interest Discussion "Modeling of Seismic Site Amplification using AI"
Reviewer	2023 ASCE Geo-Risk, Engineering Geology, Landslides, Lithology, Natural Hazards,
	Frontiers in Earth Science, Bulletin of Engineering Geology and the Environment, Arabian
	Journal of Geosciences, Advances in Civil Engineering, Stochastic Environmental Research
	and Risk Assessment, etc.
37' D '1 4	AGGEG I divided III in a contract of the

Vice President ASCE Geo-Institute Clemson University Graduate Student Organization

Member American Society of Civil Engineers Geo-Institute (ASCE G-I)

Member Earthquake Engineering Research Institute (EERI)

Member Seismological Society of America Member American Geophysical Union

LANGUAGES & SKILLS

Languages: English (fluent), Chinese (native)

Scientific Programming: Python, R, Matlab, Tcl, Git

Numerical Simulation Tools: OpenSees, FLAC, Abaqus, PFC

Geospatial Analysis Tools: Google Earth Engine, ArcGIS, GeoPandas

Remote Sensing Techniques: Unmanned Aerial Vehicle (UAV), 3D Laser Scanning, Ground-based Synthetic Aperture Radar (GBSAR)

Geotechnical Tests: Scanning Electron Microscope (SEM), Energy Dispersive X-ray, Computerized Tomography (CT) Scan, Direct Shear Test, Cyclic Triaxial Test

REFERENCES

1. Ellen Rathje, Ph.D., Professor, ASCE Fellow

Department of Civil, Architectural, and Environmental Engineering, The University of Texas at Austin Cockrell Hall ECJ 9.227C, Austin, TX, USA 78712

Phone: +1 (512) 232-3683 Email: e.rathje@mail.utexas.edu

3. Qiushi Chen, Ph.D., Associate Professor

Glenn Department of Civil Engineering,

Clemson University

320 Lowry Hall, Clemson, SC, USA 29630

Phone: +1 (864) 656-3330 Email: giushi@clemson.edu

5. Babak Moaveni, Ph.D., Professor

Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering,

Tufts University

200 College Avenue, Medford, MA, USA $02155\,$

Phone: +1 (617) 627-5642 Email: babak.moaveni@tufts.edu

7. Xuanmei Fan, Professor and Deputy Director

State Key Laboratory of Geohazard Prevention and

Geoenvironment Protection,

Chengdu University of Technology

1 Erxianqiao Rd, Chengdu, Sichuan, China 610059

Phone: +86 (182) 0816-1586 Email: <u>fxm_cdut@qq.com</u> 2. Laurie Baise, Ph.D., Professor and Chair

Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering,

Tufts University

200 College Avenue, Medford, MA, USA 02155

Phone: +1 (617) 627-2211 Email: laurie.baise@tufts.edu

4. Elizabeth Cochran, Ph.D., Research Geophysicist

Earthquake Science Center,

U.S. Geological Survey

525 S. Wilson Ave, Pasadena, CA, USA 91106

Phone: +1 (626) 583-7238 Email: ecochran@usgs.gov

6. C. Hsein Juang, Professor Emeritus, ASCE Fellow

Glenn Department of Civil Engineering,

Clemson University

Clemson, SC, USA 29634 Phone: +1 (864) 656-3322 Email: hsein@clemson.edu